Guide to the Johanna Fateman Riot Grrrl Papers 1991-2006 MSS.258
Fales Library and Special Collections
Johanna Fateman Riot Grrrl Papers
1991-2006
Fales Library and Special Collections
Fateman, Johanna, 1974-
MSS.258
7 Linear Feet in 2 manuscript box, 1 half manuscript box, 1 record carton, 3 oversize flat boxes, 1 flat box, 1 card box, 1 custom box, and 1 flat-file folder.
Johanna Fateman is a writer, musician, record producer, and business owner who was a member of the bands Le Tigre and MEN. She created zines and played in multiple bands as part of punk feminist scene in the 1990s, and after graduating from the School of Visual Art with a BFA in painting began working as a studio assistant to artists and a curatorial assistant in galleries and art spaces. In addition to writing, performing, and producing music, Fateman also writes critically, with her work featured in publications like The New York Times and The Observer. This collection consists of materials created and collected by Fateman documenting her involvement in the punk and riot grrrl scenes, including correspondence, ephemera, zines (including both masters created by and zines collected by Fateman), publicity material, photographs, video recordings, and stage outfits from Le Tigre and MEN.
Scope and Content note
This collection consists of materials created and collected by Fateman documenting her involvement in the punk and riot grrrl scenes, including correspondence, ephemera, zines (including both masters created by and zines collected by Fateman), publicity material, photographs, video recordings, and stage outfits from Le Tigre and MEN.
Immediate Source of Acquisition
Donated by Johanna Fateman in 2010, with additions to the collection in 2011 and 2015. The accession numbers associated with these gifts are 2011.258 and 2016.002.
Conditions Governing Access
Materials are open to researchers. Please contact the Fales Library and Special Collections, fales.library@nyu.edu, 212-998-2596.
Arrangement
This collection is arranged into nine series, with folders and media in Series I through IV arranged alphabetically within the individual series.
Series I. Works by Johanna Fateman
Series II. Zines and Ephemera
Series III. Correspondence
Series IV. Media
Oversize Series I
Oversize Series II
Accretion 2011: Subseries I: Works by Johanna Fateman
Accretion 2011: Subseries II: Zines and Ephemera
Accretion 2015
Biographical Note
Johanna Fateman was born in 1974 and was brought up in Berkeley, California by parents Richard and Martha Fateman. She was close friends with Miranda July (née Grossinger) in high school, which she left after her junior year at age 17 to attend Reed College in Portland, Oregon for two years. During these years and a subsequent year after leaving college in Portland, Fateman and July collaborated on the writing and publication of six issues of a zine called Snarla, a feminist art project informed by and distributed through underground punk networks -- given to women at punk shows at 924 Gilman in Berkeley as well in Portland and in Santa Cruz, California where July lived for several years. It was also available directly from the two of them via mailorder for one dollar bill, and eventually from a few record stores and from Riot Grrrl Press. While attending Reed College Fateman met video artist Sadie Benning at a screening of her work at the Portland Art Museum.
At a Bikini Kill show at the X-Ray Cafe in Portland, Fateman gave singer Kathleen Hanna a copy of issue #1 (Snarla In Love). They became close friends and Hanna moved into Fateman's house, a punk feminist communal house called The Curse. They started a short-lived band called The Troublemakers with Molly McMahon (Molly Sixteen).
In 1994 Fateman moved to New York City to go to art school. Molly Sixteen killed herself in 1995. Fateman made the zine The Opposite, Part I in the summer of 1996. It was not formally distributed outside of New York City; it was given to friends and it was sold at See Hear on St Marks Place and Printed Matter. Later that year she produced My Need to Speak on the Subject of Jackson Pollock, and Artaud-Mania! which were only given to friends, teachers, and other art students.
After graduating from the School of Visual Art with an BFA in painting, Johanna worked as a studio assistant for artists Mary Heilmann and Billy Sullivan, and from 1998-1999 was the curatorial assistant at alternative art venue Thread Waxing Space. Also in the late 90s Fateman, Hanna, and Benning started the band Le Tigre and recorded their self-titled debut album. Benning quit the band in 2000 and JD Samson joined. Le Tigre had several more releases, toured internationally, and broke up in 2005. A film about Le Tigre's touring and performances from 2004-2005 was released on DVD in 2011.
Fateman has co-owned Seagull Salon in the West Village since 2006. She continues to write critically as well as write and produce music.
Electronic music.; Feminist punk electronic music.; Punk culture.; Riot grrrl movement.; Costume.; Feminism and art.; Feminism; Correspondence.; Fanzines.; Little magazines.; Magazines (Periodicals); Benning, Sadie; Samson, J. D.; Hanna, Kathleen, 1968-; July, Miranda
- Series I: Works by Johanna Fateman
  Scope and Content
  This series consists of zines and materials created by Johanna Fateman in the mid-1990s. Some folders include construction elements for zines, such as flats.
  - Artaud-Mania (Flat), Undated (Box 1, Folder 1)
  - It Grosses Her Out - Flat and Copies, October 1994 (Box 1, Folder 2)
  - Love vs. Light, Live Version, Undated (Box 1, Folder 3)
  - My Need to Speak on the Subject of Jackson Pollock, December 1996; Various (Box 1, Folder 4)
    General
    One item removed and placed in oversize
  - The Opposite, Part I Flat Copy and Covers, Undated (Box 1, Folder 5)
  - Snarla, 1993; Various (Box 1, Folder 6)
- Series II: Zines and Ephemera
  This series includes punk, feminist, and riot grrrl zines and magazines created by Johanna Fateman and others.
  - Address Book, Undated (Box 1, Folder 7)
  - Alien, Number Eleven, Undated (Box 1, Folder 8)
  - Andy Warhol's Video & Television, Whitney Museum of Modern Art Exhibition Catalog, 1991 (Box 1, Folder 9)
  - Angst Comics, 1993 (Box 1, Folder 10)
  - Antechamber, Issue #1, Undated (Box 1, Folder 11)
  - Axilas, Undated (Box 1, Folder 12)
  - Butt, Number Four, Summer 2002 (Box 1, Folder 13)
  - Crass Mail, 1993; January 20, 1994 (Box 1, Folder 14)
  - Desperate Times, #8, Undated (Box 1, Folder 15)
  - Double Bill, Undated (Box 1, Folder 16)
  - Doublle Bill, No. 3, Undated (Box 1, Folder 17)
  - Double Bill, The Final Issue, Undated (Box 1, Folder 18)
  - Erase Errata Tour Diary, Europe, 2002 (Box 1, Folder 19)
  - Face, #9, Undated (Box 1, Folder 20)
  - Fag School, #2, 2006 (Box 1, Folder 21)
  - Funeral, February 1994 (Box 1, Folder 22)
  - Hothead Paisan: Homicidal Lesbian Terrorist, Undated (Box 1, Folder 23)
  - Hothead Paisan: Homicidal Lesbian Terrorist, #19, 1995 (Box 1, Folder 24)
  - I (Heart) Amy Carter, #5, Summer 1994 (Box 1, Folder 25)
  - Jailhouse Turn Out, June 15, 1996 (Box 1, Folder 26)
  - Kutt, Number Two (Box 1, Folder 27)
  - Kutt, Number Three, Winter 2003 (Box 1, Folder 28)
  - La Rousse, Part 1, February 4, 1994 (Box 1, Folder 29)
  - Le Tigre Stickers, Undated (Box 1, Folder 30)
  - Lost I.D., Undated (Box 1, Folder 31)
  - Lately, with Correspondence, Undated (Box 1, Folder 32)
  - Molly Zuckerman Zine, Undated (Box 1, Folder 33)
  - Mucho Coolan'!, Undated (Box 1, Folder 34)
  - Mud Flap, #1, Undated (Box 1, Folder 35)
  - Mud Flap, #2, Undated (Box 1, Folder 36)
  - The New Yorker, Miranda July, September 18, 2006 (Box 1, Folder 37)
  - No More Miss Les, The Ten Points, Undated (Box 1, Folder 38)
  - The Official Kathleen Hanna Newsletter, February 16, 1996 (Box 1, Folder 39)
  - Plunger, #3, December 1994 (Box 1, Folder 40)
  - Pocho Magazine, Issue 7, 1994 (Box 1, Folder 41)
  - Pocho Magazine, Number 8, 1997 (Box 1, Folder 42)
  - Pocho Magazine, Number 9, 1998 (Box 1, Folder 43)
  - Polemia, Pre-Copy, Undated (Box 1, Folder 44)
  - Practice More Failure, Issue No. 3, July 2004 (Box 1, Folder 45)
  - Prone to Fall, Number Four, Undated (Box 1, Folder 46)
  - Riot Grrrl Press, Fall/Winter 1997 (Box 1, Folder 47)
  - Riot Grrrl Press, Catalogue, Early 1994 (Box 1, Folder 48)
  - Riot Grrrl Flyer, April 14, 1993 (Box 1, Folder 49)
  - Scum Manifesto by Valerie Solanas, 1991 (Box 1, Folder 50)
  - Soda Tragedys Do-It-Yourself Crookbook, August 20, 1994 (Box 1, Folder 51)
  - Starfucker, #3, September 1999 (Box 1, Folder 52)
  - Tales of Blarg, Issue Six, 1993 (Box 1, Folder 53)
  - Tobis' Veil, #2, Undated (Box 1, Folder 54)
  - Topical Treatments, Premiere Issue, Summer 1997 (Box 1, Folder 55)
  - Topical Treatments, Issue Two, Winter/Spring 1997-1998 (Box 1, Folder 56)
  - Trouble Makers Flyer, Undated (Box 1, Folder 57)
  - Untitled Zine 1, Undated (Box 1, Folder 58)
  - Untitled Zine 2, January 15, 1998 (Box 1, Folder 59)
  - Welcome to the Valley, Number 5, Undated (Box 1, Folder 60)
- Series III: Correspondence
  This series includes correspondence regarding Fateman's zines.
  - Fanzine Correspondence, 1996-1998 (Box 1, Folder 61)
  - Hate Mail, 1994; February 7, 1997 (Box 1, Folder 62)
  - Jones, G.B., November 13, 2002 (Box 1, Folder 63)
  - Kathleen [Hanna], 1994-2000 (Box 1, Folder 64)
  - Smith, Jen, February 27, 1997 (Box 1, Folder 65)
  - Vail, Tobi, March 15, 1997 (Box 1, Folder 66)
- Series IV: Media
  This series contains 5 VHS tapes and 1 audio cassette.
  - Subseries A: Access Copies
    Conditions Governing Access
    Audiovisual materials have not been preserved and may not be available to researchers.
  - Subseries B: Originals
    - Side A: Girl Gangs Must Rule All Towns Side B: Josie, Undated; ID:258.0001 (Box 2, Media ID:258.0001)
    - Benning, Sadie - Video Works, Volume Three, 1995,1998; ID:258.0002 (Box 2, Media ID:258.0002)
    - Hardy, K8: 3 Videos Made by K8 Hardy, Undated; ID:258.0003 (Box 2, Media ID:258.0003)
    - Knuckle Down, Undated; ID:258.0004 (Box 2, Media ID:258.0004)
    - Spit Myself Out, Undated; ID:258.0005 (Box 2, Media ID:258.0005)
    - Swallow, 1995; ID:258.0006 (Box 2, Media ID:258.0006)
- Oversize Series I
  - Do Something, Asshole, Undated (Box 3, Folder 1a)
    Removed from the folder containing "Snarla" in Series I
  - My Need to Speak on the Subject of Jackson Pollock, Undated (Box 3, Folder 1b)
    Removed from folder of the same name in Series I
- Oversize Series II
  - Bikini Kill Shirt, Undated (Folder 6 Right)
  - Hot Tub, September 16-October 24, 1998 (Box 3, Folder 2)
  - Practice More Failure, Issue No. 3 Poster, July 2004 (Folder 5 Right)
    Removed from "Practice More Failure, Issue No. 3" folder in Series I
  - "Sexuality Harassment" by Halley, Janet, Undated (Box 3, Folder 4)
  - Take Fright Poster, Undated (Box 3, Folder 5)
  - Julie Ruin Lyrics, undated (Box 3, Folder 6)
    Removed from Kathleen Hanna correspondence, Box 1, folder 64
- Accretion 2011: Subseries I: Works by Johanna Fateman, 1996, Undated
  - Artuad Mania [Paste-Up Master], 1996 (Box 4, Folder 1)
  - Opposite-Realted Material/Orginal Artwork/Photo Material, 1996, Undated (Box 4, Folder 2)
  - Unpublished Zine Parts/Love Vs. Light [Original Artwork], Undated (Box 4, Folder 3)
  - 3-D Freak Volcano-Artist Statement/Original Artwork, Undated (Box 4, Folder 4)
  - My Need To Speak On The Subject Of Jackson Pollock [Flats/Photographs/Slides], Undated (Box 4, Folder 5)
- Accretion 2011: Subseries II: Zines and Ephemera, 1995, Undated
  - Molly Ann McMahon aka Molly 16 (Box 4, Folder 6)
  - It's Not Your Turn Yet [Shaun Cottle], 1995 (Box 4, Folder 7)
  - Riot Grrrl Ephemera, Undated (Box 4, Folder 8)
- Accretion 2015
  This series consists of photographs, publications, and artifacts created or collected by Johanna Fateman documenting her involvement in the bands Le Tigre and MEN, as well as the larger punk and riot grrrl scenes. Materials include band t-shirts, performance props, stage outfits, photographs from Le Tigre tours in the early 2000s, and clippings from music magazines featuring or reviewing Le Tigre.
  Arrangement
  The materials in this series have not been arranged by an archivist; materials are arranged in the order in which they were received from the donor.
  - Miscellaneous Snarla Correspondence, 1992-1995 (Box 5, Folder 1)
  - Miscellaneous Riot Grrrl Related Photos, 1993-2000 (Box 5, Folder 2)
  - Tracy and the Plastics, circa 2000-2006 (Box 5, Folder 3)
  - 2000 Tour (Box 5, Folder 4)
  - T-Shirt Designs, circa 1998-2004 (Box 5, Folder 5)
  - Press Materials, 1999-2000 (Box 5, Folder 6)
  - Email Interviews, 2000 (Box 5, Folder 7)
  - Michigan Womyn's Music Festival (MWMF) Protests, 2001-2002 (Box 5, Folder 8)
  - Swim With the Dolphins, 2001-2003 (Box 5, Folder 9)
  - Some Fan Mail, circa 1998-2006 (Box 5, Folder 10)
  - Sadie, circa 2002 (Box 5, Folder 11)
  - Miscellaneous Le Tigre Photos, circa 1998-2006 (Box 5, Folder 12)
  - Drawings for The Opposite: Part I, 1996 (Box 5, Folder 13)
  - Sampler Charts, circa 1998-2006 (Box 5, Folder 14)
  - Press for Jennifer, 2000-2001 (Box 5, Folder 15)
  - International Originals, 2001-2005 (Box 5, Folder 16)
  - Domestic Originals, 2000-2001 (Box 5, Folder 17)
  - JD's Lesbian Calendar, 2003 (Box 5, Folder 18)
  - ANP Quarterly, 2006 (Box 5, Folder 19)
  - Media Coverage of Le Tigre, 2000-2004 (Box 5, Folder 20-21, Box 6, Folder 1-4)
  - Tour Photographs, circa 2001-2002 (Box 7, Box 8)
  - Phone Stage Prop Created by JD Samson, circa 2002 (Box 9)
  - Band T-Shirts and Outfits, circa 1998-2004 (Box 10)
  - Stage Outfits, circa 1998-2006 (Box 11)